<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The representation of the case of Sir John Lenthall, Knight, in his late sufferings</title>
            <author>Lenthall, John, Sir, Knight.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41658</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355732</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355732</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110635</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47681)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110635)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1744:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The representation of the case of Sir John Lenthall, Knight, in his late sufferings</title>
                  <author>Lenthall, John, Sir, Knight.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Yeare, 2654 [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging: pages 38, 39, and 41 numbered 36, 40, and 37 respectively.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, and with print show-through, with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lenthall, John, --  Sir, Knight.</term>
               <term>Prisons --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110635:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REPRESENTATION OF THE CASE OF Sir <hi>JOHN LENTHALL,</hi> Knight, IN HIS LATE SUFFERINGS.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 2654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110635:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110635:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the life of man could be waf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on in his voyage of this World, with a conſtant Gale of happineſſe, we ſhould love that too well, yet ſhould bee unhappy in this, that wee ſhould never be brought to a remembrance of our ſelves and condition, nor to a due acknowledgement of that ſupreame power in whoſe hands wee are, but as Chaffe before the Wind, to whoſe juſt and wiſe wil, we ought abſolutely to reſigne our ſelves, without murmuring or grudging. He drawes light out of darkeneſſe, and conſolations out of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. His corrections are inſtructions, which leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon my troubles taught mee, and my experience found in my late darke and ſad condition, when my God was graciouſly pleaſed conſtantly to give me inward comfort in my unparralleld ſufferings, when there was nothing but outward appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of diſcomfort, there being riſen up againſt me malicious and blacke mouthed adverſaries for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110635:3"/>Priſoners, who were for their mutinous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour while they were in Priſon, ſent by the Judges to Newgate, whoſe falſe tongues were dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Poyſon of Aſpes, and yet they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved encouragement and countenance from Mr. <hi>Fountaine,</hi> who (being advanced in his owne thoughts to a high place) ſhould have preferred Juſtice before partiality and ſelfe ends, yet were Heavens diſpenſations ſoe wiſely diſpoſed, that theſe fiery trialls did purifie my innocency, and make it appeare as I hope brighter. Their proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions againſt me, were beyond meaſure, violent malicious and bloudie. But their falſe accuſations when they were filed, did onely poliſh truth and made it more ſplendid. They belched out the fowleſt accuſations that their owne wicked ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations could deviſe or invent, hoping thereby, to make mee odious to all good and pious men: but their injuſtice could not obſcure the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties juſtice, the bright beames whereof diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the blacke Clouds of their helliſh plots; and ſo diſplayed them to all mens eyes, and eares, that hee hath clothed them with ſhame, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (I truſt) my innocency and credit with them that were Auditors and ſpectators.</p>
            <p>Their calumnies were very fierce (and thats the way which malice thinkes the beſt to prevaile) and they rayſed a triple accuſation of a dangerous and horrid nature againſt me. Firſt, the breach of publicke truſt, which ſtruck at my reputation and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110635:3"/>fortune. The ſecond, that of delinquency, which ſtrooke at my being in the Common-wealth, and the well being of my poſterity. And the third, that grand one, of Murther, which did ſtrike not onely at my life in this world, but at my happineſſe in the world to come. Which accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations were moſt forcibly carried on, and injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly countenanced.</p>
            <p>But becauſe every man cannot poſſibly bee ſatisfied of all perticulars by generall rumor and report, I thought it charity to them, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to my ſelfe, faithfully and impartially to ſet downe all the paſſages of that cruell proſecution, which I ſhall doe, with all the truth and modeſty, that a juſt vindication will permit.</p>
            <p>If that malice which hath brought this affliction upon me, could have been contented with ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and legall proſecution; and if my eſtate and livelihood were the things onely in queſtion, and my good name not ſullied with infamous &amp; filchy ſlanders, I ſhould in all probability rather patiently have ſate downe under my ſufferings, then have beene induced to lay open my condition unto the world. But ſince I cannot but be of opinion, that many perſons both of worth and conſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to reſt in the firſt repreſentations, may by this meanes bee brought to a juſt knowledge of the whole matter; and conſequently bee reduced to the moderation of doing what is but juſt, and that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110635:4"/>my good name (which to an honeſt man ought to bee dearer then life) may bee in ſome meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived; I could not but put downe as well the true circumſtances of my condition, as the violent and paſſionate proceedings of my proſecutors againſt me.</p>
            <p>I have been theſe twenty three yeares together Marſhall of the (Kings Bench, now the) Upper Bench Priſon, by Letters Patents under the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> wherein, as I am inwardly ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to have behaved my ſelfe uprightly and legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo till this ſtorme overtooke me, I hope it was without infamy or reproach. But it is the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of ſuch employments as mine, that wee muſt neceſſarily in doing our Offices, raiſe up to our ſelves Enemies. For it is ſo difficult, if not impoſſible, to carry our ſelves even between Creditor &amp; Debtor, that there is no avoyding or it, but one of them will be diſſatisfied. For if the Debtor be either unruly, or unable to put in ſecurity, for his true impriſonment, &amp; ſo kept ſafe, he ſtraight crieth out of Reſtraint &amp; hard uſage; but if hee put in ſecurity, &amp; lie in the Rules, or legally goe abroad about his occaſions with a Keeper, then does the Creditor crie out of too much liberty, &amp; it may be files a Bill for an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. So that let a man carry himſelfe with all the care &amp; circumſpection which is poſſible, he ſhall be ſure to meet with clamors &amp; enemies; And theſe ſo much the more in regard that being perſons either in low condition, or decayed fortunes, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it ſomewhat either of eaſe or pleaſure, to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110635:4"/>revile or vex thoſe whom they look upon as the inſtruments of their misfortunes.</p>
            <p>After the diſſolution of the former Parliament, then ſome perſons did take upon them a power (by what authority or order I know not) to enquire into all matters concerning Priſons, and Keepers of Priſons, by vertue of whoſe power I was ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to appeare before them, which I obeyed. But it was a wonder to me (who had been a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant to the Parliament in their moſt doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and difficult times, and who had beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in all their Commiſſions, and ſtucke to them thorowout, when others declined them) to ſee Mr. <hi>Fountayne</hi> in the Chayre, one of the moſt active for the late King, and one by whoſe power and intereſt at Oxford, my place was given away, for diſobeyng a Warrant of the late Kings, dated the 23. of November 1643. for the diſcharge of <hi>William Cobb.</hi> Yet humbly ſubmitting (as it was my duty) to the Authority over mee, and withall weighing with my ſelfe the Right that all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours have to call whom they pleaſe to their aſſiſtance; beſides, hoping that Mr. <hi>Fountaine</hi> had manifeſted unot them his hatred to his former principles and courſes; I, with all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I could, prepared my ſelfe to give the beſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that lay in my power unto that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee.</p>
            <p>The Generall things they fell upon, were firſt, About the Liſt of my Priſoners, a perfect and full Copy whereof I delivered in. Next, about the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110635:5"/>Extent and Liberty of the Rules of the Priſon, by which means (as was alleadged) there are many Eſcapes occaſioned, and Creditors extreamly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed, if not abſolutely defrauded. In anſwer to this, I only ſayd, That the Priſon houſe being ſo little, as that it is not able to contain a fourth part of the Priſoners, my Predeceſſors in their ſeverall times, and that alwaies by permiſſion and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Judges, uſed to lodge them (having firſt taken ſecurity for their true impriſonment) in the houſes about, and that they call the Rules: which as it avoides a grand inconvenience (for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe every perticular man muſt have a perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Keeper which were a charge to him unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, or elſe the Marſhall of the Priſon were to maintaine them, and ſo he ſhould bee a loſer by his office) ſo it brings this great advantage and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity to the Creditor, that the ſecurity being dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the debt, it is thereby ſtrengthened, and the Creditor in better probability to recover his own. For if any eſcape be made, I am liable to paye the debt, and upon recovery had againſt mee at Law, I either reſort to the ſecurity, or turne it over to the Creditour, by which meanes many have reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their debts, which probably otherwiſe they had not done. But theſe bonds being of late doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee within the Stat. 23. H 6. (though ever before held good and ſo often adjudged) many have under this prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce eſcaped, or violently broke Priſon; and thereby both defrauded the Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110635:5"/>and occaſioned great damages to bee given againſt the Marſhall.</p>
            <p>And although I haue done nothing, but what by Law was formerly accuſtomed and juſtifiable, yet I deſire a difference may bee made, betweene voluntary and involuntary eſcapes; that is to ſay, eſcapes happening either by my granting too much liberty, or by negligence, or connivence; and thoſe which in deſpite of the ſtrength of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the care and dilligence of the watchmen, are oftentimes made by deſperate Perſons, groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning under their wants, and impatient of reſtraint: and therefore I appeale to all the Nation, whether there was yet ever any debt recovered againſt mee for an eſcape, which I have not ſatisfied. And as I cannot bee denied the liberty of a true Engliſh man, to make my beſt defence, when I am implea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at Law, which in many caſes plentifully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves me, as 3. Edw. 1. Cap. 3.1. Edw. 2. Cap. 10. <hi>Bonitons</hi> caſe Cooke. 3. part. pa. 67. <hi>Ridg ewayes</hi> caſe, Cooke. 3. Page. pa. 54. <hi>Wesbies</hi> caſe. So if it can bee proved that any eſcape hath beene wilfull in me, or that I ever tooke a penny of money for granting any illegall liberty, I ſhall bee content to ſuffer all that which the malice of my adverſaries would inflict upon me.</p>
            <p>Nor is it enough to ſay that the beſt and moſt conſiderable Priſoners ſhould bee put into the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110635:6"/>houſe, for ſo the more inſolvent ſhould bee ſet at randome, and their debts by this meanes become deſperate: for the ſecurity of the others (beſides their owne reputation) renders them as ſafe in the Rules, as if they were cloſe; and there is many a man that will rather be bound in a bond of 1000 l. for a mans true impriſonment, then be bound with him in a bond of 100 l. debt.</p>
            <p>But when they came to deſcend into perticular matters, it was very ſtrange to me, to ſee Mr. <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> (more like a feed Lawyer, or an enraged e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, then a ſober Judge) afford ſo much counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to all Petitions and complaints that came in againſt me, to ſtretch matter further then by Law they would endure. And when I deſired but Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of Petitions that I might bee the better ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to make my defence, utterly to refuſe mee, and put me to anſwer upon the place: which when I endeavoured to doe, as well as the ſmalneſſe of the time, and my owne ſur-priſall would permit me, I was ſundry times reviled, many opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpeeches, both againſt my ſelfe and my neereſt relations, were publickly uttered, without the leaſt controle or check. The witneſſes which I bought in order to my juſtification, were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced; Mr. <hi>Fountaine</hi> in the meane time, privately comenting and gloſſing his own concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as I have reaſon to conceive, and writing them downe, ſo that things ſeemed to bee carried
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110635:6"/>on (I will not ſay by deſigne or injuſtly) meerely in a manner to compaſſe my ruine. The Petitions and charges that came in, to looke on the number, were a great many, on the weight of them, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few. Some of them are either ſo falſe, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, that they are not worth mentioning heere, as I have done otherwhere; ſome the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtating of my caſe, immediately detects the malice and impertinency. But ſince that there is one particularly inſiſted upon as a matter very horrid and ugly, I ſhall not forbeare to ſet it down, that by the eſtimate of this grand buſineſs, an account may be taken of the reſt.</p>
            <p>And the buſineſſe ſtands thus:</p>
            <p>One <hi>John Guyet</hi> was committed to the Upper Bench Priſon Feb. 10.1650 upon an Action of Treſpaſſe at the ſuit of <hi>Edmund Child,</hi> but not upon Judgement or Execution. This <hi>Guyet</hi> broke the Priſon houſe (hee being in cloſe Priſon, together with foure others) in the night time, having bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned downe the window with hot irons, poyſoned a fierce Maſtiffe, and given ſome opiate medicin to the Watchman, where with he layd him in a dead ſleepe all night: and by that meanes the ſayd <hi>Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et</hi> went away in the night time, by Ladders of Ropes, provided for that purpoſe, as is prooved by many witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Thereupon <hi>Child</hi> brings his Action of the Caſe againſt Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthall</hi> for 579 l. for the Eſcape, and at a Tryall at Guildhall had given him by the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110635:7"/>Jury (who faild not to bee his friends at a dead lift) the whole money and damages 584 l. 13 s. 4 d. For reliefe of the verdict, I preferd a Bill in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, to which he put in an unperfect anſwer, and ſate in contempt. Hereupon I moved at the Roles for an Injunction to ſtop proceedings at Common Law, which the Maſter of the Rolls being ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that <hi>Child</hi> in equity ought to have no more of me then he could have recovered of <hi>Guyet</hi> at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, and for that a man may lay an Action of 10000 l. and yet poſſibly not recover 100 l. &amp; for that this was the onely courſe I had left, to make <hi>Child</hi> confeſſe what his debt really was; (hee having already in his anſwer confeſſed 100 l. was given by the verdict more then was due to him) the Injunction was granted, as well for theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as that it had been the conſtant practiſe and rule of hat Court, to grant Injunctions upon the lkie occaſions. And whether I had not reaſon to ſeeke for reliefe in Chancery or no, let any man judge: For though there were abundance of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table circumſtances, which I could not make out at my tryall; yet by that (among other things) which I ſayd before, the equity was very evident.</p>
            <p>Nay this Caſe among others was referred by the Parliaments order of the ninteenth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1652, to the Juſtices of the Upper Bench, who upon hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the whole matter, declared me not in fault for the Eſcape, and the buſineſſe therefore onely
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110635:7"/>for the Chancery: wherein being a Court of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity I was onely relieveable. For certainly the verdict was a ſtrange one, and the oppreſſion that lies upon mee by the meanes of it as heavy, and of as ill example, as can be poſſible.</p>
            <p>This is the great buſineſſe as to the execution of my Office; but becauſe the rage of my enemies was not content to ſtay heere, but would ſtrike at my life, as well as my livelihood, they have ſet abroach an old buſineſſe voted ſcandalous by the Parliament many yeares agoe, and threatened to try mee for my life about it. The buſineſſe ſtands thus. <hi>George Smithſon</hi> was committed to the Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Bench Priſon <hi>Iune</hi> 13.1637. where hee carried himſelfe with ſuch extreame diſorder, that in the yeare 1640. hee was put into the common Goale, where hee was not onely ſo troubleſome, but alſo ſo dangerous to the Priſoners, that they Petitioned for his removall. Heereupon I ordered him eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry night to bee put into the houſe which is ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for unruly Priſoners: there continuing his old manners, hee was kept for ſome time, all which ſpace he was fed with victualls ſent from my own Table, and the Stewards of the houſe, had expreſs order to take care that he ſhould be conſtatly relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. He died the 5 of <hi>September</hi> 1640. A Crowner ſate upon him, a Jury was ſworne, ſix Priſoners, and ſix neighbours, who found that <hi>Smithſon</hi> died by the viſitation of God, and not other wiſe, or by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110635:8"/>any other meanes, as appeares by the Record.</p>
            <p>I thanke God, I have this comfort yet left mee, that I can ſay, I find not in my heart to thirſt after blood. And certainly theſe people, had they not beene blinded by their owne malice, and carried on by an extreame defire of my ruine, might have found out ſomewhat more probable to have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed their perjuries about, then for to ſay, that I ſhould hazard, my ſalvation, my reputation, my life, the well being of my Wife and Children, and all this for the blood of a poore Lunaticke in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whom till that time, I had never known, and from whoſe death I could draw no advantage.</p>
            <p>The very ſame men that have reviv'd this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt me, before that Committee, brought the ſame complaint to the Parliament ſeven or eight yeares ſince. At which time, it was exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with all induſtry, ſcrutiny, earneſtneſſe, and integrity poſſible: all their owne examinations, and thoſe of what witneſſe they could produce, were taken, and ſeverall perſons were admitted by that Committee, in the name and behalfe of the City, to take notice of all proceedings. The Committee after a full hearing made the Report to the Parliament, that they found the accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons falſe, and proſecuted without cauſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the 5 of <hi>September</hi> 1645 they voted, that the complaints were raiſed, and proſecuted, without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110635:8"/>any ground at all, falſly, maliciouſly, and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly; and that <hi>William Pendred, Edward Jenks, Hanna</hi> his wife, <hi>James Freez,</hi> and <hi>Stephen Prat,</hi> were principall inſtigators and proſecutors of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; and doe deſerve ſevere and exemplary puniſhment, and accordingly referred it to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to conſider what exemplary puniſhment were fit to be inflicted upon them.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed did they vote it malicious, without ground: for <hi>Freez</hi> and <hi>Jenks,</hi> with one <hi>Magick</hi> (who was a great ſtickler in the buſineſs, though not ſo openly as the other) having been formerly Priſoners in the Upper Bench, and there very unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and miſchievous, the Judges did remove them to Newgate, which firſt kindled in them that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that hath ſeverall times ſince attempted my life.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, their wickedneſſe was ſo reſtleſſe, that though they ſaw how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle they were able to ſatisfie any juſt men of the ground of their complaints, they had the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to renew the buſineſſe againe at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for the Armie, who alo upon examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on voted, <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. 1649. to the ſame purpoſe as the Parliament had formerly done; yet after all theſe repulſes they have againe brought it to Mr. <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> Committee, where it ſeemes, it received freſh entertainement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:110635:9"/>Theſe are the two principall things, out of which with ſome other helps, (I will not ſay Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of his owne) Mr. <hi>Fountaine</hi> hath ſtuffed his Papers, and at laſt harche'd a Report. But however it is, though it be not fitting for me to ſay, that he carried himſelfe there rather like an Adverſarie then a Judge, ſo it ſhould feeme hee hath a mind, by the carriage of this buſineſſe, that men ſhould find him turne from a Judge to a Solliciter. For this report of his, he very aſſidiouſly promoted to the Committee of the laſt Parliament, who upon the report ordered <hi>July</hi> 25. 1653. that I ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the ſame Committee the next day, which was Tueſday following at 3 in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, and bring with mee a perfect liſt of the names, ſirnames, places of laſt abode, of all the Priſoners in cuſtody, ſince the laſt liſt in print; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all Bonds, Statutes, Judgements, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants of Aturney, to acknowledge Judgements to Creditors or others in their behalfe.</p>
            <p>Heerupon I Petitioned the Committee, Teuſday <hi>July</hi> 26. 1652. in regard I had not received their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der till late the laſt night that I might have Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of Reports, and Petitions, and bee admitted to put in my defence in writing, or by my Counſell.</p>
            <p>But being expreſly commanded to attend the Thurſday after, I accordingly did ſo, and carried in the liſt; but ſhewed them that I could not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110635:9"/>in the Bonds, by reaſon they were the onely ſecurity which enabled mee to performe ſeverall truſts ſetled out of the Office, and the onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence I had againſt all Eſcapes, ſued, and to bee ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But the Committee preſſed mee for a poſitive anſwer, whether I would deliver them or no, and though I Petitioned for it, would grant mee no longer time, then the next morning, for my poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive anſwer; which I was to deliver to the Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by 10 of the Clocke. According to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, next morning being Friday, I delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Letter to the Chairman, with a Paper of Reaſons encloſed, Why I could not in diſcretion, and ſafety, deliver in the Bonds: both which, ſince I am ſo much concerned in them, for better ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction follow thus.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Humble Anſwer of Sir <hi>John Lenthall</hi> Knight, Marſhall of the Upper Bench Priſon.</head>
                  <p>IN obedience to the commands of this Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Committee whoſe Perſons and Power in all humility I ever ſhall have in high eſteeme, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offer, that the poſſibility that the Marſhall of the Upper Bench hath for the preſervation of ſuch Priſoners as ſhall bee thereunto committed (by reaſon of the ſmallneſſe and unſafeneſſe of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon houſe) are onely ſuch collaterall ſecurities as by his owne induſtry and endeavours he can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from perſons that ſhall engage for the true
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110635:10"/>impriſonment of the Priſoners; which ſecurities (howſoever good in Law as he humbly conceives) are onely perticularly belonging to himſelfe, and to his owne private eſtate, and to ſuch others as have likewiſe intereſt in thoſe ſecurities as well as himſelfe, and no way concerning the publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and by the Law of this Land are diſpoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by him, and ſuch other perticular perſons to whom they in right and equity doe belong, as any other perſonall ſecurities to any other perticular perſon: that this preſent Parliament by their moſt pious and Religious Declaration lately ſet forth to the contentment of many thouſands of this Nation, encourages him (with all thankefull acknowledgement) to aſſure himſelfe that as the Parliament the higheſt and ſupreame power of the Nation, hath declared that they will be as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Lives, Eſtates, Liberties, Juſt rights and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of all others, as they are of themſelves and their poſterities, ſo this honourable Committee who are a part of that honourable body will not be offended, if that hee the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthall</hi> ſhall on his and the others behalfe, preſume upon that honourable favour and grace which the ſaid Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath with ſuch abundant care offered to the people, and therefore cannot in juſtice or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity deliver up ſuch ſecurities, which cannot bee uſefull or advantagious unto him by the Law (as appeares by his former reaſons humbly offered to the Committee and other grounds) if taken from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110635:10"/>him without a particular Act of Parliament therein to relieve him. This being thus humbly offered without the leaſt diſregard to the power of this Committee, or diſreſpect to any of their perſons, whom as becomes him in the place wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God hath placed you, hee ſhall ever honour: this in all humility aſſuring himſelfe of juſtice and equity according to the knowne right of Law and property.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>IOHN LENTHALL.</signed>
                     <date>
                        <hi>July.</hi> 29. 1653.</date>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Reaſons humbly offered and preſented to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Committee for Priſons and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, wherefore the Bonds and ſecurities taken for the true impriſonment of Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthall</hi> Knight, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench Priſon, cannot ſafely bee delivered out of Sir <hi>Iohn Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalls</hi> hands.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. FOr that many of the ſaid Bonds and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon Eſcapes made, are already delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Creditors, thereby to recover their Debts due from the Priſoners; and Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſtands enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by his promiſe to deliver divers more.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:110635:11"/>II. For that as ſcone as the Priſoners ſhall take notice their ſeourities are out of Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthals</hi> power, they will and may make Eſcapes; and Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> having no other way to reſtraine them, or to ſecure himſelfe, other then by his Bond and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, ſhall be left without remedy.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. For that there now being ſeverall Actions of Eſcape depending againſt Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthall,</hi> amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to 100<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0 l. and ſeverall recoveries had, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> hath no other meanes to ſecure his Perſon and Eſtate from the ſayd Actions, and recoveries, but by the ſayd Bonds and ſecurities, many of which he hath delivered to his Atturnies to put in ſuit to bee indemnified from the ſayd actions and recoveries.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. For that the ſayd Bonds and ſecurities are made to him in his name, for his indemnity, and ſuable onely by him and in his name, and can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be releaſed by him.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. For that the ſayd Bonds &amp;c. are not forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or to bee ſued untill after Eſcapes brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthall,</hi> ſo that if the ſame ſhould be delivered out of his hands, the Priſoners, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, Sureties, and Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthall,</hi> may bee much damnified.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. For that upon the diſcharge of Priſoners
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110635:11"/>(which is daily) the ſaid Bonds and ſureties are to bee delivered up, otherwiſe the ſureties may bee endangered, and the Priſoner damnified upon his Counter-ſecurity given by him to his ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. For that every Defendant hath liverty to crave Oyer of the condition of the Bond, upon which he is ſued, before he plead; which Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> not having in his hands to produce, will be delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his ſuit, or loſe the benefit of his Actions.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. For that the Bonds and ſecurities taken for true impriſonment are Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthalls</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right and property, which hee hopeth this honourable Committee will inviolably defend.</p>
                  <p n="9">IX. For that the ſureties, who are moſt of them tradeſmen in this Citty, and live by their Credits, and will bee bound for a Priſoners true impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they will not be bound with him for any money, when they ſhall perceive their names are publiſhed, and their bonds put to other u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes then they intended them, will preſently call in their Bonds, and that will bee a meanes to deter all others from being bound; which will prove a very great prejudice to the Creditor.</p>
                  <p n="10">X. For that ſuch bonds and ſecurities, as are in Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> hands were given to him by the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110635:12"/>and his ſureties, by way of truſt and upon condition that no uſe ſhall be made thereof but in caſe of Eſcape. And therefore the Priſoner having made no Eſcape, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> cannot without breach of truſt part with their ſecurities.</p>
                  <p>The morrow after, which was Saturday, the thirtieth of <hi>July,</hi> the houſe was made acquainted with this my anſwer, who thereupon made an Order for my commitment to the Serjeant at Armes, to anſwer to ſuch matters as ſhould bee objected againſt me; and another Order that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant <hi>Dendy</hi> ſhould take the care and cuſtody of the Priſoners, which he accordingly did, my ſelfe being apprehended with a Warrant from Serje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant <hi>Birkhead,</hi> under which durance I continued, though I did humbly beſeech them in regard of the multiplicity of the troubleſome and entangled buſineſſe that lay upon mee, and for that I knew not what might bee brought out againſt mee, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had ſo many yeares to doe in a troubleſome Office, to bee pleaſed for to take off this reſtraint from mee, which certainly as I did not ſee what prejudice could ariſe from it, all my eſtate and livelihood lying at the ſtake, and it concerning me ſo neerly to make out my intereſt, ſo had it beene to me a deed of very great mercy and compaſſion. For as it would have beene a meanes to ſave mee from a great charge, which in the miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition I was in, laye heavy upon mee, ſo would it have enabled mee to goe about to make ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110635:12"/>againſt what might have beene brought againſt me, in behalfe of the Common wealth, as that I might thereby enjoy the benefit of the Law, and the freedome of a Native Engliſh man.</p>
                  <p>The great offences which they alledged againſt me as is before ſet down, being onely broched, but nothing proved, I did little expect ſuch a reſtraint ſhould have beene put upon me as to impriſon my body, and to put Serjeant <hi>Dendy</hi> into the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Office before I were heard or had leave to make my defence. And I cannot but ſay this by the way, that it being my miſ-hap to bee the miſerable preſident in this caſe, in what doubt may it leave all other Officers who have acted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the knowne Lawes of the Nation, (as I ever did,) and what ſecurity can they imagine to themſelves, if upon every alteration they ſhall be called in queſtion, for actions done by vertue of Lawes in force?</p>
                  <p>For my part, I doe aver that what I did in the execution of my Office, was nothing but what the Rules of the Court (to which I was a ſervant) permitted, what my predeceſſors had conſtantly practiſed, and what was not againſt the Lawes that then ſtood in force, and notwithſtanding the overflowing malice of my adverſaries, they could never prove any one thing againſt mee to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:110635:13"/>Standing thus committed to Sergeant <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>irkhead,</hi> for no cauſe expreſt, I could not finde that Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant <hi>Dendy</hi> who was poſſeſſed of my Office, had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bowels of mercy, for I received this letter from him, ſent to my Priſon: Sir, I acquainted the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee the other day with your anſwer, with which they were ſo much diſſatisfied, as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to report your contempt to the Parliament; yeſterday they ſate not, but adjourned till this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoone, till when I deſired they would forbeare acquainting the houſe, for that you promiſed you would doe your endeavour, of which if you give not a reall proofe by a returne of the bookes, wherein all the names of your Priſoners with their ſecurities, &amp; place of abode are, it will be in vaine for you to think of ſecuring your ſelfe by a refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall. Sir, the complaints of ſeverall Creditors un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done by you, are very great, and our Law you know hath condemned many a man who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon hath ſuffered death, though but for the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of a ſheepe; therefore all things conſidered, it concernes you not to contemne any longer the Authority of the Parliament, who if incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as you give them juſt cauſe to bee, neither you nor yours know what evill to them a day may bring forth. Sir, the Committee being to meet this afternoone betweene 2 and 3 a clock, I have ſent the bearer on purpoſe to receive your anſwer which is expected by.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>E. DENDYE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110635:13"/>By this Letter it may be conceived in what a ſad condition I was, whereby it plainly appeares that Serjeant <hi>Dendye</hi> had never any intention to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore my Office, but ſtill to have kept it from me. To which purpoſe he uſed all his power to get the bookes and ſecurities into his hands; the bookes I delivered, but not the Bonds given to me for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Priſoners, which if I had given up, I had beene left naked of my defence of ſuites for Eſcapes, and I doubted, that many Bils might be filed againſt mee before the next terme, for Eſcapes made in Serjeant <hi>Dendyes</hi> time, as it afterwards happened, many declarations being brought againſt mee for them, for which if I had parted with my ſecurities, there might have beene ſo much recovered againſt me for his neglects, as might have ruined mee and my poſterity, which was the principall cauſe that I did not deliver them, and not diſobedience to the Parliament, to which I was prepared to proſtrate my ſelfe in all ſubmiſſion, not doubting but that they would in good time take into conſideration my innocencie, and withall the number of innocent perſons, that were involved in my ruine, and that they would ſo mixe their juſtice with mercie, that they would againe reſtore mee to my liberty, and juſt right. But the malice of Mr. <hi>Fountaine</hi> did hang ſtill as a danke Cloud overmy head, from which I knew I was to expect a ſtorme; nor was I deceaved, for it was growne to that malicious and unchriſtian
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110635:14"/>height, that though when the accuſation concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Murther of <hi>Smithſon</hi> and others were heard, and eagerly examined before him and his fellowes of that Committee, he expreſſed upon a full and open hearing his opinion of the improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the charge and the untruth thereof. Yet not willing to let ſo much as a ſhadow paſſe, which might deſtroy mee, hee inſerted and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woove this charge into his furious Report to the Counſel of State, as an high crime againſt me, and fit for examination to whom hee delivered it.</p>
            <p>Afterwards aſſoone as the late Parliament ſate, this Report of Mr. <hi>Fountaines</hi> was tranſmitted (I doubt not but by his meanes and ſolliciation) to the Committee of the Parliament for Priſons and Priſoners. The ſame Committee the 18. of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1653. having the day before brought in a charge againſt me, which was then read.</p>
            <p>The maine heads thereof conſiſted of breach of Truſt, Delinquency, and Murther, which I having ſpoken of before, I ſhall at the preſent mention no otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>The two firſt Charges the Parliament referred back to the Committee, and the matter of bloud, to fowr Juſtices of Peace for Surrey, to examine the ſame, and to proceed therein according to Law and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110635:14"/>Saturday the 20. of Auguſt, the Committee ſent for mee to the Star-Chamber, where they ſate, &amp; there delivered me a Copy of the Charge of all Referred unto them, excepting Delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and appointed me to bring them ſuch an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as I would ſtand to on Thurſday the 25. fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which accordingly I obeyed, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in my Anſwer ſubſcribed with my Name.</p>
            <p>The ſame Thurſday two of the aforeſayd Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices ſigned a Warrant to hear the cauſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Murther and bloud, the Munday follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at the White Lion at Lambith, where I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with my witneſſes, but <hi>Hannah Jenks</hi> and the reſt of her malicious complices were not to be found.</p>
            <p>I cannot omit one paſſage which happened there at that time, which was, that there being then preſent, a poor Beggar Woman, who heard ſomething of the buſineſs of that meeting, and did ſpeak ſome words tending to cleare my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, whereof the Juſtices being informed, they preſently ſent for her, and committed her to the County Goale (though ſhe totally denyed the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation) where ſhee lay in great wants and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry five weeks at the leaſt; and though ſhe offered them often Bayle, ſuch as ſhee was able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and made ſeverall Petitions unto them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110635:15"/>her ſad condition, yet ſhee could find no mercy in all that time, till by reaſon of wants of bread and other neceſſaries, ſhe fell very ſick, and was neere the inſtant of periſhing, when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcended to Bayle her out, but afterwards did not proſecute her at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hannah Jenks</hi> and her witneſſes ſayling to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, it occaſioned another appointment, which by their Warrants dated the ſecond of September was to be on Monday after, being the fifth day, at the Bull head Tavern in Southwark; there I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them with my Parliament Keeper, where I found Miſtriſs <hi>Jenks,</hi> her husband, and <hi>James Freeze,</hi> and ſome other complices, ſuch as bribes, promiſes, and ſimilitude of wickedneſs could ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about her, where indeed her nimble tongue like a Trumpet, ſounded forth ſuch loud noyſes and falſities (which much retarded the buſineſſe of that day) that I began to believe that ſhe would ſwear up to the heigth, according to her former cuſtome, that my innocency (how white ſoever) might be clouded by her oaths.</p>
            <p>But this day wee were put off and adjourned to the ſame place on Friday following, where Mrs. <hi>Jenks</hi> with her tribe ſayled not. They were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led preſently in by the Juſtices, and were private with them almoſt all the afternoone, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being examined, though there bee very
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110635:15"/>great reaſon to beleeve that they were not then examined at all, but only asked queſtions to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented paper which was ſent unto them from Mr. <hi>Fountayne,</hi> which was the rather beleeved, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he that was pretended there to be the Clark that writ, and to have taken the Examinations, could hardly read them when they were put into his hand for that purpoſe. But howſoever, mee thinks, this privacy was not conſonant to the old Law of England, which in caſes of Life, brings Witneſſes face to face, and admits croſſe Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, the Law being moſt eſpecially tender of Life, and never intending that ſhould bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without all poſſible Defence of the accuſed party.</p>
            <p>But at length (to give the Divell his due) I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving attended on this ſecret Conference all the Afternoon, my ſelfe and witneſſes were called in, and thoſe I brought were ſuch as I doubted not, would convince the Juſtices of the falſity of the teſtimony againſt mee, and cleare mee of the crime.</p>
            <p>But I no ſooner entred, but I found a Warrant ſigned and ſealed by the Juſtices, for my Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the County Goale, which my Keeper oppoſing (as in right he ought) they threatned to impriſon him, and called for a Conſtable to carry me away. But none being then preſent, the better
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110635:16"/>to gaine time while they could get one, (wherein they neglected no diligence) they yeelded to hear two Witneſſes on my ſide, whoſe teſtimony was ſufficient to have ſatisfied them. But ſtill they forget not with all earneſtneſſe to call for a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable to Hurry mee away. But at laſt upon much entreaty, almoſt upon the knees of ſome of my children then preſent, they prevayled with them to read the Parliament and Armies Votes, before expreſſed, about the buſineſs, whereby they were Voted falſe Accuſers, and to have corporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: And thereupon with much adoe and great difficulty, they yeelded and conſented to take Bayle.</p>
            <p>And heere I cannot but note by the way, the mercy and regularity of theſe men, who at the ſame time did, (what Nature cannot doe) ſplitt me into a double Priſoner; a Priſoner I was to the State, under cuſtody of the Supream Power, preceding theirs, and yet during that time they made a <hi>mittimus,</hi> and would have ſent mee to the Common Goale of the County, which may bee conceived a high preſumption to take mee from the Parliaments immediate Officer, and ſend mee to another Priſon, without their leave or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</p>
            <p>Obſerve by the way, heere is a Warrant ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without examination of the party accuſed.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110635:16"/>Next the Juſtices offer to take a Priſoner out of the hands of that power by whoſe Commiſſion they ſare.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, notwithſtanding the mallice and falſity of theſe Proſecutors appeared by the Votes of Parliament and Army, they Bayled me after they had made a <hi>mittimus</hi> to commit mee for Murther.</p>
            <p>On Tuſeday the 30. of Auguſt I was ſent for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the Committee of Parliament at the Star-Chamber, who there Examined Witneſſes to proove their Charge againſt mee; as they did alſo on Saturday following: At which time I was injoyned to bring in proofes to juſtifie and maintaine my Anſwer.</p>
            <p>On the 8. of <hi>September</hi> following I brought my former anſwer, wherein I quoted the objections made againſt mee in my charge, and to every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular put in a diſtinct anſwer, with the names of the witneſſes in the margent which were to prove the ſame.</p>
            <p>But I ſhould have told you before, that during the examination of witneſſes againſt mee, <hi>Freeze</hi> &amp; <hi>Hannah Jenks</hi> were the chief, who were ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendently malicious, that they ſwore at any thing they thought might prejudice me: for <hi>James Freeze,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:110635:17"/>who was the chiefe witneſſe was there in the face of the Court proved to have ſworne falſe in two of his Teſtimonies, whereupon I excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as witneſſes invallid, and their evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence not to bee taken for that they had formerly in their proſecution againſt mee, beene voted by the former Parliament falſe accuſers, and to have corporall puniſhment, with which vote the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Officers of the Army afterwards concurred, upon a new complaint made to them by thoſe wretched creatures, whoſe malice was unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and reſtles.</p>
            <p>My exception to them after ſome debate was allowed good, for that they who would ſweare falſely in one thing may doe it in another.</p>
            <p>And you may gueſſe by this, that if the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt proſecutors and witneſſes, were of this ſtampe, that the other by them procured and ſuborned, were not of a much better allay, as hereafter wee ſhall have occaſion to inſtance.</p>
            <p>But ſee the inſecurity and impudency of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe and the conſtant though unexpected pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection that Divine providence ever provides for innocency, though what hath beene before allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged might have ſufficiently invalidated their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Credits before any Court of Juſtice, yet it plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed God for further diſcovery of their impious plots againſt me to ſtir up the ſpirit of one
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110635:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mr. <hi>Francis Anguiſh</hi> who was then an accidentall auditor of their violent proſecutions of me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the truth; Which was, that he being a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the Fleet <hi>Anno</hi> 1649. at which time <hi>Freeze</hi> was then alſo Priſoner there, hee often heard the ſayd <hi>Freeze, Jenks,</hi> and others, plot together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sir <hi>John Lenthall,</hi> and conclude, that they would indevour to hang him, if they could, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing him of Murthering and Poyſoning of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. But if they could not prevaile, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his life, then they would accuſe him of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency againſt the State, and by that meanes <hi>Freez</hi> and the reſt would get a ſhare of his eſtate, and that they made no queſtion, but to bring their plots to paſſe when the time ſhould ſerve, and a new Parliament ſhould ſit. Which evidence Mr. <hi>Anguiſh</hi> juſtified upon oath to the Committee; who examined him upon what grounds, or upon whoſe inſtigations he came thither to evidence for Sir <hi>John Lenthall?</hi> who anſwered that he being preſent at a former examination before them, and hearing the ſaid <hi>Freeze</hi> and <hi>Jenks</hi> ſo to proſecute him, according to their former combinations and conſpiracies, he could not in conſcience but declare the truth of that which hee had formerly heard and knowne them to conclude. But hee averd, as truth was, that he never had any reference to Sir <hi>John Lenthall,</hi> nor was never mooved to give this Teſtimony by any but his owne conſcience: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Mr. <hi>Anguiſh</hi> ſeverall other witneſſes inſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110635:18"/>their unjuſt endeavours and falſe accuſations againſt Sir <hi>John Lenthall;</hi> and as theſe fiery trialls have already cleared me, ſo I doubt not, but time the mother of truth, will make it more appeare. But Mr. <hi>Fountayns</hi> mallice was of a harder mettall then to be blunted with all this; for of a Judge (as he formerly took it upon him) hee was now become a Sollicitor, dayly attending, incenſing, and informing the Committee againſt mee: and his ſpite was ſo ſucceſſefull, that hee prevayled to have Bills poſted up at Weſtminſter Hall Gate, and other places, inviting all that had any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt mee, to repaire to the Committee where they ſhould be heard.</p>
            <p>I was commanded to attend the Committee two or three dayes every week, from Auguſt, till the beginning of December following. By which time they had received, heard, and conſidered all accuſations and complaints which malicious ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or ſuborning ſuggeſtors, could bring or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure: and the Committee were ready to draw up their Report and to make it to the Houſe, of all their proceedings herein with all poſſible ſpeed, but the Parliament reſigning their power the 12. day of December, into the hands of his Highneſſe the Lord Protector, I was plunged into a gulfe of miſery, as never any diſtreſſed perſon was. The power that layd mee in Priſon and ſequeſtred my eſtate, they were diſſolved. Thoſe that had mee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110635:18"/>in Cuſtody, neyther would, nor could releaſe me. I was at a ſtand, and amazed: Remedy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe I knew of none; yet notwithſtanding, ſome worthy and conſcientious men of the Committee taking my ſad condition into their pious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, whereof the Chayrman was one, though they had reſigned their power, yet were pleaſed for conſcience and truths ſake, to declare their Judgements and Opinions, by a Certificate under their hands, bearing date the 6. of January 1653. wherein they did certifie, That the Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sir <hi>John Lenthall</hi> in Parliament, conſiſted of three ſeverall heads. The firſt, for Eſcapes of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. The ſecond, for Delinquency. The third, for Murther.</p>
            <p>For the Eſcapes, they Certifie to have beene very few, in reſpect of the great clamours made againſt him; and that thoſe were meere matter of Law, and properly triable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and determinable there.</p>
            <p>For the Cauſe of Delinquency, they Certifie, That by the Judgement of the former Parliament, 15. September 1645. the ſame was reſolved ſcandalous, and the Proſecutors in that Cauſe to deſerve exemplary punniſhment; which Votes of Parliament were after confitmed, by the Votes of the Councel of the Army 1649. upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the Perſons and Witneſſes in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110635:19"/>Complaint, and we find nothing in proofe to the contrary.</p>
            <p>For the murther, We judge that Charge to be moſt malicious againſt Sir <hi>John Lenthall,</hi> and that he is innocent of any ſuch crime, and we do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſaid Charge to have been proſecuted with much malice againſt him, and the teſtimony of the Witneſſes to be altogether invalid; to which Certificate they ſubſcribed their names.</p>
            <p>I being left thus deſtiture and diſconſolate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my liberty reſtrained in Priſon, and deprived of my Eſtate, and conſequently of all ſubſiſtance, It pleaſed God to prepare means to turn my mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into joy, by putting the civill Sword into my Lord Protectors hand, I addreſſed my ſelf unto his Highneſs by my Petition, and had the happineſs to be one of the firſt fruits of his juſtice, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly referred it to his honourable Councel; they with the like diſpatch appointed foure of themſelves a Committe to heare and examine my Cauſe, by whoſe command I attended on Monday the 16 of <hi>January</hi> where they tooke the buſineſs into conſideration, and with much inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, Juſtice, and prudence, examined the ſtate of my accuſation, as it ſtood before the late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So conſciencious and ſcrupulous they were, that they not only deliberately peruſed all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that I produc'd, but moſt judiciouſly (as inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110635:19"/>to heare at both eares) ſent for all the Notes and Examinations which remained in the hands of the Clerke of the Committee of Parliament, by which they might be truly inſtructed of all accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and informations againſt mee, which the Clerk accordingly brought in, and upon a through and mature conſideration thereof, thoſe honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſons were pleaſed (after they had with great diligence and patience peruſed and examined all that could be ſaid for or againſt me) to make their Report to the Councell the 24. of <hi>January</hi> how they found the State of the buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>The Lords of the Counſell debating the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe upon the Report ordered the 27. of the ſaid <hi>January,</hi> that it ſhould be referred to the Lord Chiefe Juſtice <hi>Roll,</hi> and to other Juſtice or Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Upper Bench, to examine all Complaints againſt Sir <hi>John Lenthall,</hi> ſo as the ſame may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in a legal way, &amp; therby they were requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to take ſuch courſe for diſpoſing the cuſtody of the Priſon and Priſoners as may be moſt ſecure and advantagious for the Creditors, and is agreeable to Law and Juſtice: and certainly if that way had been thought of before, Serjeant <hi>Dendy</hi> had not now had ſo many Eſcapes brought againſt him, nor ſo many men in all probabilities endangered of ſo many conſiderable D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bts, nor my ſelfe have had ſeverall Declarations brought againſt me for Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capes made and ſuffered in Serjeant <hi>Dendy's</hi> time
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110635:20"/>when hee was poſſeſſed of the Priſon.</p>
            <p>By Vertue of the Order of the Counſell, the Lord chiefe Juſtice, and Mr. Juſtice <hi>Aske,</hi> ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Serjeant <hi>Dendy</hi> and my ſelfe to appeare before them on Munday the 30 of <hi>January,</hi> where wee both attended with out Counſell, and after a full debate and examination of our reſpective intereſts and titles in the ſaid Office, His Lordſhip and Mr. Juſtice <hi>Aske</hi> were both pleaſed to declare that Sir <hi>John Lenthall</hi> had a good title in Law, which neither Serjeant <hi>Dendy</hi> nor his Counſell ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did or could denie.</p>
            <p>Thereupon the Lord chiefe Juſtice and Mr. Juſtice <hi>Aske</hi> did make their Certificate to the Lords of the Counſell, Dat. the 13 of <hi>Febru</hi> 1653. that upon hearing Counſell of both ſides, they found that Sir <hi>John Lenthall</hi> had a good title, which Serjeant <hi>Dendy</hi> did not deny, and that they were informed and it was confeſſed by both parties, that divers Priſoners, who were in Priſon, when Serjeant <hi>Dendy</hi> firſt entred into the cuſtody of the Priſon, are now abſented, to the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of their Creditors, and diſhonour of the Law, and of the Upper Bench in perticular, wee have thought fit to ſettle Sir <hi>John Lenthall</hi> in the Office of the cuſtody of the Priſon and Priſoners, which courſe wee conceive to bee moſt ſecure and advantagious for Creditors, and moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Law and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:110635:20"/>The Judges did alſo declare in open Court the 11 of <hi>February,</hi> that the Lord Protector and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell had appointed them by their order to heare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny complaints againſt Sir <hi>John Lenthall,</hi> ſo that they might bee determined in a legall waye, and that they alſo required them to ſettle the cuſtody of the Priſon and Priſoners, according to Law and Juſtice; and therefore they did declare Sir <hi>John Lenthall,</hi> to bee Marſhall, and admitted him to ſit in Court, and to take the cuſtody of the Priſon, and Priſoners pon him, and ordered a Rule of Court to bee entred to that purpoſe which was done accordingly. By vertue whereof I was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of my Office and livelihood, and after ſome ſtrugling with Serjeant <hi>Dendy</hi> was ſuffered quietly to enjoy it. And I cannot but heere acknowledge and extoll Gods wonderfull and abundant good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who out of the depth of his mercy, looked upon mee in the depth of my miſeries, and out of the ſtrength of his power delivered mee from the malice of my potent enemies who were ready to devoure me and ſwallow me up.</p>
            <p>Rationall and conſcientious men might thinke this had beene enough to have cleared any man: the Law (which I ever threw my ſelfe upon, and the Law is the ſupreame directory and definitive ſentence of all our actions) had reinveſted mee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which was my owne propriety, and would have inflicted a condigne puniſhment upon mee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110635:21"/>in any thing wherein I had offended.</p>
            <p>That honourable Court of the Upper Bench had power to take cogniſance of any offences I ſhould commit, whoſe eares are ever open to heare and relieve the injured and oppreſſed, which might have incited my adverſaries to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained there, whoſe mouths were not ſtopped in ſeaven yeares before from thundring out their falſe clamours againſt me in all places. But behold the inſatiable malice which my wicked adverſaties bore againſt mee (which will lie like burning coales on their owne heads) ended not heere, my eſtate and inheritance had ſtood their ſhock. But by Gods protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they could not ſhake it, therfore their wicked ſpirits muſt now rove higher; they conſpire to ſtrike at my life againe, and endeavour to waſh their hands in my blood.</p>
            <p>And indeed it was one of the moſt accurſed pieces of wickedneſſe in all the world, to endeavour to plunge mee into ſuch infamy, who have lived, as I hope, in honeſt repute in my Countrey, that have ſeene many children and childrens children, that have beene thought worthy by the higheſt powers to bee imployd in all commiſſions, and almoſt all Committees in the County, where I have dwelt ſo long, and ſate upon the Bench there, to bee brought to bee tryed at that Bar where I had ſo long ſate, and into the danger of ſo ſhame full an
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110635:21"/>end as our Law ordayned for Murther; and to ſay more, the Divine Law threatens for this offence, I heartily wiſh it may not fall heavy upon the heads of my accuſers and proſecuters.</p>
            <p>But now the Aſſiſes begin in Southwarke, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared there according to my Bond, but no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors ſhewing them ſelves. I deſired they might be called and their Recogniſances might be retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which the Court granted, and ſo called them, whereupon one witneſſe appeared wheſe name was <hi>Robert Ell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> upon whoſe Teſtimony it was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the whole manifeſtation of the buſineſſe would lie: this man being urged by the Court to prefer his Bill of Jndictment againſt me, he openly profeſſed he knew nothing againſt mee, and could not tell how to preſerre a Bill, and ſo refuſed to proſecute, ſaying further, that hee was inforced by the Juſtices to whom the Parliament referd it to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Bond, otherwiſe he ſhould not have done it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward Jenks</hi> another of theſe Witneſſes, and one of the chiefe contrivers of this plot alſo appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, who being required to prefer a Bill, hee told the Court that he came not to prefer any Bill, but was aſſured by Mr. <hi>Blackwell,</hi> one of the Juſtices then ſitting upon the Bench, that an Indictment ſhould be drawne, and preferred, and coſt him nothing, and that he and the other Juſtices requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to proſecute, which he refuſed to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:110635:22"/>Thereupon hee was ſo impudent to tell the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to his face in the open Court, that he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to ſend him to the Goale, and was ready to doe it, if hee refuſed to bee bound to proſecute, the fear whereof compelled him to be bound.</p>
            <p>But ſee the bold ſpirits of theſe men, who durſt charge ſo fowle, unjuſt, and malicious a matter, in open Court, upon a Juſtice then preſent, and ſitting upon the Bench. But the Judge required <hi>Jenks</hi> eyther to prefer a Bill, elſe he ſhould forfeit his Recogniſance; hee denied it, and plainly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that hee knew nothing of his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge againſt me, and that hee was compelled by the Juſtices to doe what he did, and that his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution was meerly by their command.</p>
            <p>Upon this the Court commanded the Clerk of the Aſſizes to draw up an Indictment, and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Jenks</hi> to give Inſtructions, which was done as far as their Evidence would bear, But <hi>Jenks</hi> diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it. The Judge commanded him to goe to any of his own Counſell, but hee did not doe it, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as was conceived could he finde any matter to ground an Jndictment upon, and ſo none was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred; whereupon I was acqitted by Proclamation the laſt morning before the Aſſiſes were ended and adjourned.</p>
            <p>I having ſuffered ſuch an infamy and diſgrace, I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110635:22"/>conſidered with my ſelfe and Counſell, which way to redeem and vindicate my wounded credit and reputation. And for that end I was adviſed to Indite the Proſecutors for Conſpiracy againſt my Life, at the next Quarter Seſſions holden for the Courty of Surrey, which I accordingly did. The Bill was found againſt them all, and they ſtand convicted.</p>
            <p>And that every one might ſee what kinde of people they are, I ſhall tell you that ſince thoſe proceedings, <hi>Freeze</hi> being imployed in ſome place about the Exciſe Office, hee hath beene put out thereof, being convicted of bribery, and deceiving the State; <hi>Oliffe</hi> and <hi>Magewick</hi> have beene ſince convicted and ſentenced for bribery and perjury, at the ſuit of other men.</p>
            <p>But I cannot omit to expreſſe ſome paſſages of Mr. <hi>Fountayne,</hi> which came lately to my hands from Mrs. <hi>Jenks,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Somerſcall,</hi> in a paper which they ſent mee the firſt of Auguſt 1654. by them ſubſcribed, wherein they directly expreſſe that they were urged with great earneſtneſs by Mr. <hi>Fountayn</hi> to proſecute me, which they refuſed to do, yet Mr. <hi>Fountayn</hi> was reſtleſſe, &amp; could not be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied till he compelled them to come in; for which purpoſe he meeting Mrs. <hi>Somerſcall</hi> in Weſtminſter Hall, one Saturday evening (for theſe are the words of the Certificate) hee asked where is Mrs. <hi>Jenks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:110635:23"/>and commanded her to tell her that wee have been in jeſt with Sir <hi>Johns</hi> buſineſs all this while, but now we will go on with it in earneſt, which he ſo proſecured, that hee got an Order from the Committee, for the Witneſſes to go into Surrey, which they refuſed to doe; then Mr. <hi>Fountayne</hi> ſayd to the Committee, wee muſt force the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to goe into Surrey, or elſe wee ſhall never cut him off. Behold the greedineſs of this bloud-thirſty man, who when he could find no Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that could or would proſecute, he would raiſe ſome up, and compell them. Oh! I cannot but wonder how this mans heart contracted ſuch an unparalleld malice againſt me, who never had dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with him, but often retained him in the times of his practiſe as my Counſell, and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him as my friend. And truly I cannot in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity but bee ſo much his friend ſtill, as to pray to God that the judgment pronounced againſt bloud-thirſty men, may not fall upon him.</p>
            <p>The 22 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1654 <hi>Hannah Jenks</hi> ſent ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Paper unto mee to this effect, that whereas, ſhe had formerly proſecuted me with divers accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of ſome Capitall crimes and offences, theſe are to certifie that ſhe received the notion of them from others informations, and by their onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement and inſtigation did purſue thoſe allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt Sir <hi>Iohn Lenthall.</hi> But inſomuch that they do not lie in my proper and peculiar know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110635:23"/>I doe heerby utterlie renounce and abjure all farther proſecutions and proceedings againſt him, to which Paper ſhe ſubſcribed her name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore credible witneſſes. And theſe are the perſons that led up the chiefe place in my ſeverall accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and by theſe you may eaſily gueſſe the reſt.</p>
            <p>I have heere preſented the large heapes of my diſaſters and troubles, my Priſon thoughts and Priſon experiences; I had infinite afflictions and yet infinite comforts, light out of darkeneſſe, and joyes out of ſorrowes; the Lord manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to mee in my ſeceſſions and impriſonment, which was but a ſequeſtration from the world, that I might the more converſe with God, and this done hee manifeſted his glory and power in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering mee from the Jawes of the Lyon and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whelps. I had in all my troubles a ſtrong truſt and confidence in my God who hath drawne mee out of many waters and through a braſen wall. To him I referre my ſelfe, vengeance is his, and he will repay it, and if man ſhall not thinke fit to make me ſatisfaction for theſe wrongfull expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (which I hope they will) yet they are in Gods hands, to whoſe providence and protection I who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly referre my ſelfe; for the Lord is my ſtrength and my ſhield, my heart truſted in him and I was hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, therefore my heart ſhall rejoyce, and with my ſong will I prayſe him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
